<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Motivation on Luis Miguens Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.miguens.one/tags/motivation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Motivation on Luis Miguens Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.miguens.one/tags/motivation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Forms of control and motivation in regulated aerospace organizations</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/06/forms-of-control-and-motivation-in-regulated-aerospace-organizations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/06/forms-of-control-and-motivation-in-regulated-aerospace-organizations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An organisation can be defined as a group of individuals working together to achieve one or more goals (The Open University, 2019). Therefore, we must engage people to work on the goals that the organisation considers essential. Unit 2.1 of this MBA (The Open University, 2014a) introduced Knights and Willmott&amp;rsquo;s findings, which identified four types of control mechanisms: direct supervision, rules and procedures, culture and performance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The author&amp;rsquo;s experience relies on a software firm in the aerospace sector, doing contractual work for governmental-type organisations. In the author&amp;rsquo;s knowledge, two control types overlap: &amp;ldquo;rules and procedures&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;performance&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critique Tony Watson’s article</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/06/critique-tony-watsons-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/06/critique-tony-watsons-article/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Watson (1996), in his article, propose an ethnographic experiment. His objective is to study the engagement of his students in the motivation theories he teaches.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I admire Watson&amp;rsquo;s attempt to design an experiment as controllable in dealing with the irreproducibility of an experiment that treats human behaviour. That falls into the domain of a complex system. As we discussed in Unit 2, &amp;ldquo;Every person is a world&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During my life and my previous studies in System Thinking  (The Open University, 2016), I noted that it is complicated to separate the &amp;ldquo;self&amp;rdquo; component from the system to study. In Watson&amp;rsquo;s case, his inquiry about the study of better ways to teach motivation will irremediably change him about his teaching approach, making the experiment not reproducible anymore.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
