<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Books on Luis Miguens Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.miguens.one/categories/books/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Books on Luis Miguens Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.miguens.one/categories/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Notes book: Spend Less, Invest More, and Live Free: A Guide to Financial Freedom</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2023/04/notes-book-spend-less-invest-more-and-live-free-a-guide-to-financial-freedom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2023/04/notes-book-spend-less-invest-more-and-live-free-a-guide-to-financial-freedom/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spend less than you earn – invest the surplus – avoid debt.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Do simply this, and you&amp;rsquo;ll wind up rich. Not just in money. If your lifestyle matches or, god forbid, exceeds your income, you are no more than a gilded slave.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As individuals, we only have one obligation to society: To make sure we and our children are not a burden to others. The rest is your personal choice. Make your own and make the world a far more interesting place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>59 Seconds: Think a little, change a lot</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2021/06/59-seconds-think-a-little-change-a-lot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2021/06/59-seconds-think-a-little-change-a-lot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My highlighs of the book: &lt;strong&gt;59 Seconds: Think a little, change a lot&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Richard Wiseman&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-1---happiness&#34;&gt;Chapter 1 - Happiness&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We all get used to what we have very quickly. Buying a new car or a bigger house provides a short-term feel-good boost, but we quickly become accustomed to it and sink back to our pre-purchase level of joy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;About 50 percent of your overall sense of happiness is genetically determined,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Getting to Yes: Negotiating Agreement Without Giving In</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2021/06/getting-to-yes-negotiating-agreement-without-giving-in/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2021/06/getting-to-yes-negotiating-agreement-without-giving-in/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are my notes of &lt;strong&gt;Getting to Yes: Negotiating Agreement Without Giving In&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;by Roger Fisher and William Ury&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-dont-bargain-over-positions&#34;&gt;1 Don’t Bargain Over Positions&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Arguing over positions is inefficient&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bargaining over positions creates incentives that stall settlement. In positional bargaining you try to improve the chance that any settlement reached is favorable to you by starting with an extreme position, by stubbornly holding to it, by deceiving the other party as to your true views, and by making small concessions only as necessary to keep the negotiation going.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bargaining with the Devil: When to Negotiate, When to Fight</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2021/06/bargaining-with-the-devil-when-to-negotiate-when-to-fight/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2021/06/bargaining-with-the-devil-when-to-negotiate-when-to-fight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Notes of the book:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bargaining with the Devil: When to Negotiate, When to Fight&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;by Mnookin, Robert&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, for an act to be evil, the perpetrator must intend to inflict harm. Carelessness is not enough. Second, the harm must be very serious. I use the word grievous to connote harms that are severe. Third, the infliction of harm must lack an adequate justification or excuse.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;interests&#34;&gt;Interests&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are my interests? What are my adversary’s interests?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>El arte de no amargarse la vida</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2021/06/el-arte-de-no-amargarse-la-vida/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2021/06/el-arte-de-no-amargarse-la-vida/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Estas son mis notas de un libro de Rafael Santedreu. Su modo de enfocar la vida ayuda a poner todo en perspectiva cuando sientes que te estas ahogando.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-sinopsis-obtenida-de-amazon&#34;&gt;La sinopsis (obtenida de Amazon)&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rafael Santandreu explica que muchos de los problemas emocionales actuales son causa de una mala filosofía de vida. Con gran facilidad nos creemos deprimidos, ansiosos o muy desgraciados. El arte de no amargarse la vida cuenta que todos estos trastornos emocionales podrían calificarse de terribilitis. En nuestra sociedad tenemos muchas creencias que nos hacen ser infelices como que si no tienes pareja eres desdichado o que hay que tener un puesto de trabajo muy importante para realizarse.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
