<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Strategy on Luis Miguens Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.miguens.one/tags/strategy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Strategy on Luis Miguens Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.miguens.one/tags/strategy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Alignment of managers’ actions and shareholders’ interests</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2020/01/alignment-of-managers-actions-and-shareholders-interests/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2020/01/alignment-of-managers-actions-and-shareholders-interests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although there is no miraculous panacea, there are three main tools for dealing with the agency problem:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Increasing disclosure requirements reduces the informational asymmetry between the agent and the principal, limiting managers&amp;rsquo; ability to prioritise their own selfish goals.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Creating a close relationship between company performance and directors&amp;rsquo; remuneration. Their compensation package could be a function of the profits generated. Alternatively, directors could receive part of their compensation in stocks or call options, which would align their incentives with the shareholders&amp;rsquo; objectives.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The introduction of corporate governance rules could, to some extent, force directors to act in the best interest of the company.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The area of corporate governance is defined as the rules that govern how the directors interact with each other inside the company for effective management and handle the directors&amp;rsquo; interactions with the shareholders&amp;rsquo; desired direction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conflict of interest: Shareholders vs Managers</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2020/01/conflict-of-interest-shareholders-vs-managers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2020/01/conflict-of-interest-shareholders-vs-managers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some stakeholders interest is not exclusively monetary. An example of such is &lt;a href=&#34;https://policy-practice.oxfam.org/resources/partnerships-in-fair-trade-reflections-from-a-case-study-of-cafe-direct-130427/&#34;&gt;Oxfam and Cafe Direct&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; initial pursuit of promoting the Fairtrade brand.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The above is not very common, and the working assumption is that the shareholders&amp;rsquo; objective is to maximise the wealth via the capital increase of the shares or the dividends. On the other hand, we should hypothesise that managers are more interested in their wealth and work security with the minimum effort possible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Core challenges of operations in a small aerospace software firm</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/09/core-challenges-of-operations-in-a-small-aerospace-software-firm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/09/core-challenges-of-operations-in-a-small-aerospace-software-firm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary-of-the-core-challenges&#34;&gt;Summary of the core challenges&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order to analyse the areas that need more urgent action in operations, we will apply the concepts of market-qualifiers and order-winners from Hill 2005 and introduced by  (The Open University, 2012). Afterwards, we will analyse the limitations of growing operations or scalability&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;qualifiers&#34;&gt;Qualifiers&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is defined as &amp;rsquo;entitle it to be considered by a customer&amp;rsquo;; in other words, the minimum threshold to be accepted by a customer. The organisation currently meets some of these criteria demanded by the public tenders, such as the curriculum of the staff, competence and geographical location. An element that disqualifies the organisation is the speed of delivery, and therefore a limitation in the future of the company&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic capabilities in small software firms</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2018/06/dynamic-capabilities-in-small-software-firms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2018/06/dynamic-capabilities-in-small-software-firms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I wish to summarise and critique a paper I found quite insightful.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Mathiassen, L. and Vainio, A. M. (2007) &amp;lsquo;Dynamic capabilities in small software firms: A sense-and-respond approach&amp;rsquo;, IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management, vol. 54, no. 3, pp. 522&amp;ndash;538 [Online]. DOI: 10.1109/TEM.2007.900782&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The paper describes two organisations in different phases of expansion. Both are in the category of small companies in the field of mobile applications.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The paper starts by defining the object of study, small software firms, depending on integration and reconfiguration capabilities to operate in high-velocity markets. This type of companies&amp;rsquo; constraints is limited resources (schedule, fixed costs) and a high dependency on a few big players. The paper takes as a base the Sense-and-Respond approach to managing dynamic capabilities of Haeckel (1995). The study relies on interviews with CEOs, the Department Managers and Team Leaders of two firms with different levels of evolution, named &amp;ldquo;Starter, Inc&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Mature, Inc&amp;rdquo;. Also introduces that successful adaptive organisations can monitor (Sense) environment signals quickly and translate into action (Respond) in three areas:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
