<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Systems_thinking on Luis Miguens Blog</title>
    <link>https://blog.miguens.one/tags/systems_thinking/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Systems_thinking on Luis Miguens Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.miguens.one/tags/systems_thinking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>System Thinking about a Situation of Concern</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/06/system-thinking-about-a-situation-of-concern/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/06/system-thinking-about-a-situation-of-concern/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;system-thinking-about-a-situation-of-concern-practical-example&#34;&gt;System Thinking about a Situation of Concern: Practical example&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Defining a system as a set of interacting components integrated in a whole, with structure that are related (directly or indirectly) to each other, behaviour and interconnectivity in which part or processes are connected, and any changes affect the whole, we can see how our SoC with management focus on the profitability and employees with a focus in professional development and learning are competing situations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critique of Communities of Practice</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/04/critique-of-communities-of-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/04/critique-of-communities-of-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;critique-of-communities-of-practice&#34;&gt;Critique of Communities of Practice&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The examples of Communities of Practice presented in (Blackmore, 2010) do not provide a practical implementation in a business environment and is lacking information about how CoP could translate in profit for an organisation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We have seen that CoP can translate in profit in an indirect approach, via employee satisfaction and reducing turnover rates of the company.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We could also argue that the different interpretations of CoP make it challenging to apply the concepts or to take complete advantage of the benefits that the communities of practice could offer. Nonetheless, that is expected as the module deals with complex situations that cannot be solved with a “recipe” approach of classical project management. In this context, Communities of Practice are a framework providing ideas on how to develop a system to tackle complex situations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strengths, weakness and missing elements of the theory of communities of practice</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/04/strengths-weakness-and-missing-elements-of-the-theory-of-communities-of-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/04/strengths-weakness-and-missing-elements-of-the-theory-of-communities-of-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;strengths-weakness-and-missing-elements-of-the-theory-of-communities-of-practice&#34;&gt;Strengths, weakness and missing elements of the theory of communities of practice&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We can discuss that the strengths of a community of practice are to provide a framework of ideas regarding the “how” to organise a system in which members can share ideas and develop themselves to proficient professionals. For example, without Wenger’s model, I would have overlooked the role those business developers could exercise in a community of practice as brokers of ideas and information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taking a design turn</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/04/taking-a-design-turn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/04/taking-a-design-turn/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have seen that in contrast to a systematic approach, there are no templates in the systemic approach. (Ison, 2010) introduces two orders in the learning system. The first order is characterised by a knowledge transfer, while the second order is about creating the environment to allow the student or practitioner to learn by itself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The transition from the first order mentality to the second order is what it is called ‘a design turn’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Project management vs System Inquiry</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/04/project-management-vs-system-inquiry/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/04/project-management-vs-system-inquiry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From my previous studies in the module T848 in The Open University, I was introduced to quadrants in project management approaches. According to (Fernandez, 2016), a project is classified according to a binary answer to two characteristics: goal and solution, as summarised in figure (2):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blog.miguens.one/img/project_management.png&#34; alt=&#34;Project Management quadrants&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Figure 2: Project characteristics quadrants. Extracted from (Fernandez, 2016) &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We can appreciate the similarities of a project with unclear goal and unclear solution with the words of (Ison, 2010): “Thus, unlike most projects, a systemic inquiry does not specify outcomes or deliverables before it starts – though it may specify process or timing milestones – and thus maintains an openness to surprise, adaption and an underlying emotion of uncertainty…”&#xA;(Fernandez, 2016) adds that in quadrant 3, no business value is guaranteed and introduces a variation of project managing with shorter linear and template-based solutions. I agree, therefore, with (Ison, 2010) rationale and critique of a “projectified” world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My understanding of System Inquiry</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/04/my-understanding-of-system-inquiry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2019/04/my-understanding-of-system-inquiry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After several examples during the course of Systems Thinking, part of Open University MBA, we can see that traditional approaches to project management had failed in tackling some difficult situations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In chapter 10 of (Ison, 2010), it is discussed that situations with several complex elements interdependent which each other, in which an internal modification of either an element or connection will result in an uncertain outcome, and where conflict is present, due to different goal of the elements of the situation and the different background (understood as history and perspective) of the stakeholders, can benefit of systems thinking approach, and therefore introducing the concept of systemic inquiry as a meta-platform or process for a project or program managing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Definitions of system related concepts</title>
      <link>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2018/12/definitions-of-system-related-concepts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.miguens.one/posts/2018/12/definitions-of-system-related-concepts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The different definitions of a system are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A system, in general, is any part of the universe which may be defined by a boundary which distinguishes it from the rest of the universe.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;https://nptel.ac.in/courses/103101004/2&#34;&gt;https://nptel.ac.in/courses/103101004/2&lt;/a&gt;, 2018)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;system (NOUN)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. set of things working together as parts of a mechanism or an interconnecting network; a complex whole.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. set of principles or procedures according to which something is done; an organized scheme or method.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/system&#34;&gt;https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/system&lt;/a&gt;, 2018)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
